<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The historie of S. Elizabeth daughter of the King of Hungarie. Written in French by Peter Mathieu and translated into English by Sr T.H.</title>
            <title>Elizabeth, fille du roy d'Hongrie. English</title>
            <author>Matthieu, Pierre, 1563-1621.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07268</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17663</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101124</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836948</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836948</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1248</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07268)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1248)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 966:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The historie of S. Elizabeth daughter of the King of Hungarie. Written in French by Peter Mathieu and translated into English by Sr T.H.</title>
                  <title>Elizabeth, fille du roy d'Hongrie. English</title>
                  <author>Matthieu, Pierre, 1563-1621.</author>
                  <author>T.H., Sir (Thomas Hawkins), d. 1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 70 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By the widdow of Hubert Anthony called Velpius,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Bruxelles :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An[no] 1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With engraved title page.</note>
                  <note>A translation, by Sir Thomas Hawkins, of the French original.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Elizabeth, --  of Hungary, Saint, 1207-1231.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="engraved_title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1248:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1248:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <q>Mulier timens Dominum ipsa <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>bitur.</q>
            <p>THE HISTORIE OF S. ELIZABETH DAVGHTER OF THE KING OF HVNGARIE</p>
            <p>Written in French by Peter Mathieu and translated into Engliſh by S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> T. H.</p>
            <p>AT BRVXELLES By the Widdow of HVBERT ANTONY called <hi>Velpius An<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1633</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1248:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1248:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HON<hi rend="sup">ble</hi>. THE LADY ENGLEFIELD THE ELDER, all happines temporall &amp; eternall.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I hauing bin en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated by a vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy gentleman, to reueivv this abſtract of a greater hiſtory, to the end it might paſſe to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique
<pb facs="tcp:1248:3"/>
vſe; And finding (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my ſlender skill in forraine tongues) that it pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually agreeth vvith the Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch, out of vvhich it vvas tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into our vulgar: and iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the ſubiect proper to our times, vvherein (as alvvayes) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples moue more then do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to actes of piety: I vvas Zealous to further the preſſe, annecting an <hi>Appendix</hi> or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynder of mine ovvne poore conceits, as I hope, not vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to the Reader. VVhich done, I eaſily reſolued to begge your La<hi rend="sup">pps</hi> Patronage of ſo pious a deſigne, eſpecially this
<pb facs="tcp:1248:3"/>
great Princeſſe, vvhoſe exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar life is here abbreuiated, being one of the firſt branches of that ſpirituall tree of Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicall S. Francis, vnder vvho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe shadovves you haue bin, and are vertuouſly conducted, in a penitentiall vvay to your great home; vvhere, by the infinite merits of our bleſſed Sauiour, you hope to enioy the revvard of your vertues, vvith other great perſonages of your fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, vvho haue humbly paſſed their pilgrimage vnder the ſame rule, not vvithout note of ſanctitie. I omit my ovvne titles of obligation, vvhich chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge
<pb facs="tcp:1248:4"/>
both my pen &amp; perſon in all duty to your La<hi rend="sup">pp</hi>. beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the diuine goodnes, vvho is the butt of your acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, his bleſsing to all your good deſires.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM</salute>
               <signed>Your La<hi rend="sup">pps</hi>. humble beades-man. G. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1248:4"/>
            <head>A COMMONITORY <hi>TO THE</hi> READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y intentions in expoſinge to publique veiwe the life of this glorious ſaint, a knowne member of the Catholique church, is by facts to ſhewe the church, <hi>a posteriori,</hi> by the effects to ſhewe the cauſe; For ſurely god would not haue bene ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous to reduce theſe wandringe ſheepe to his ſheepfold, as himſelfe in holy writt by publique proclamation witneſſeth. With an <hi>Oportet reducere &amp;c.</hi> If he could haue fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes out of it. Neither doe I thinke that any proteſtants, excepte either weake or mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb facs="tcp:1248:5"/>
puritanes, will not finde matter of edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and I hope much ſpirituall profitt, if piouſly, not curiouſly they obſerue this great Princes vertues. yet its not obſcurely known to men who deſire more vnitie of ſpiritts, eſpecially in matter of Religion, that there are too many, who ſoe much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the breaches of the church, that they will haue noe Communion, euen with the wery ſaints begotten in her. Theſe are they of whome <hi>Caſſander</hi> ſayth, that they ſoe hate the church, that they hate all good from her.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſſe, I delight not much in the ſociety of thoſe ſouldiers, who would haue (though only) the vpper garment of our ſauiour deuided amongſt them, which <hi>Euthimius</hi> calls his cloake, but I abhorre from thoſe, who will cutt his <hi>tunica in-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſutilis</hi> inner-coate, wich the <hi>Arabian</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretour calleth his shirte, or truet; which was in ſteede of a shirte beinge of wooll accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and myſtically without ſeame, without ſchiſme, and ſoe to be kept accordinge to the Prophett, and ſubiect only to a <hi>Miſerunt ſortem,</hi> in ſoe much that
<pb facs="tcp:1248:5"/>
the outragious Iewes themſelues durſt not aduenture to cutt it; yet I knowe there are too many cloaked vnder the name of chriſtians, who would rathermake more holes then ſtoppe one, euen in our ſauiours inner coate; of whome our learned Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryman <hi>maſter Selden</hi> in his <hi>Prolegome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na de ſucceſsionibus hebraeorum; Sui dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxat ingenij vi, ſacras literas temere explicantes, ridiculis atque impijs pacem Christianam no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uationibus perturbare ſolere paſsim videmus</hi> their factious witts are made the touch-ſtone of our faith: what many of them deny to the whole church, They arrogate to their owne priuate ſpiritts, which is, to haue power to declare all dubious, and more hidden texts of ſcripture, and out of them to frame newe canons of beliefe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vincentius Lyranenſis Chap:</hi> 26. tells you of them, and how to knowe them. <hi>Audies etenim quoſdam ipſorum dicere, verite, ô inſipientes, &amp; miſeri qui vulgo Catholici voci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamini, &amp; diſcite fidem veram, quam praeter nos nullus intelligit, quae multis ante ſaeculis la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uit, nuper verò reuelata &amp; ostenſa eſt: ſed diſcite furtim &amp; ſecretim, delectabit enim vos. Et item
<pb facs="tcp:1248:6"/>
cum dediceritis latenter docete, ne mundus au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diat, nec eccleſia ſciat: paucis namque conceſſa est tanti mysterij capere ſecretum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See there, how he proſecuteth it and when you haue peruſed him well, iudge if it touch not to the quicke thoſe factious ſpiritts, that deſire nothinge more then ſeparation, then ſedition in chriſt his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth: me thinkes in earneſt, he hath them at euery tourninge, for their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelty; for their inuiſibility, their ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, their priuate ſpiritt, their clanculare conuenticles, their praeiudicate cenſures of all others, their refractary reſiſtance of peace in Religion.</p>
            <p>Saint Hillarius <hi>de trin:</hi> layes open the ground of their <hi>vertigo. In deflexu motu aduerſandi ſtudium perſiſtit vbi non voluntas rationi ſubijcitur, ſed his quae ſtudemus doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam coaptans.</hi> Truth and learninge muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquared accordinge, to their inordinate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and not their affections by truth; they wreſt the ſcriptures and fathers to their contentious ends. <hi>Omnes tument, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſcientiam pollicentur</hi> ſaith Turtullian, by their ouer-weeninge conceite of themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues,
<pb facs="tcp:1248:6"/>
they ſwell and muſt breake out into botches, and infectious gangrenes to the preiudice of the wholl body of the church.</p>
            <p>Had there not bene thoſe turbulent ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritts in our country, guilty of more will then witt, we might not in vaine haue hoped longe ſince, that moſt deſired vnity in Religion.</p>
            <p>Had they reuerently propoſed venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble antiquity, they would haue found all the fathers moſt ſcrupulous in giuing the leaſt (I doe not ſay) cutt, but ſtretch to our Bleſſed ſauiour his myſtically wholl coate, which is his church according to all the fathers. Wittnes <hi>Tert: de praeſcriptionibus</hi> although afterwards he vnfortunately cutt it in peeces. <hi>Ireneus</hi> eſpecially lib. 3. <hi>Epiphanius de haereſibus</hi> throughout all, ſaint Hierome againſt the <hi>Luciferans</hi> howe zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly againſt <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> fearing leaſt any breach should be made by him, though indeed his flawes were not ſoe dangerous. as for Patronizing Origen too much, as <hi>ſaint Hierome</hi> notes, Apol: 2. and falſely attributing ſome ill opinions of <hi>Sixtus</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:1248:7"/>
Philoſopher to ſaint <hi>Sixtus</hi> Pope and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir as ſaint <hi>Hierome notes ep. ad Cteſiphontem</hi> whereby ſaint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was deceiued at the firſt, as appeares in his <hi>retractations li.</hi> 2. C. 46. and ſome other points. How feruent againſt <hi>Vigilantius,</hi> though I knowe the <hi>Magdeburgenſes Cent</hi> 4. C. 8. would plead a not guilty for him, yea to haue bin too hard for ſaint <hi>Hierome:</hi> but the truth is, he was faulty in denying all honour to reliques as ſaint <hi>Hier:</hi> there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futes him, and my Lord of <hi>VVinchester</hi> againſt <hi>Peron. Cauſabon</hi> againſt <hi>Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, ſuper annum Domini</hi> 34. nu. 140. lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly in the name of all <hi>England,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge a reuerence due to them, as ſaint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> relates of the miracles done by the earth of the holy land, which <hi>Heſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> reuerenced worthily, as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> noteth. He was faulty alſo in denying the ſaintes in heauen to pray for vs, for this all learned proteſtant diuines allowe, as conformable to all antiquity. Howe care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full was ſaint <hi>Cyprian</hi> in this maine point, though once indeed he gaue a ſcratch to our Bleſſed ſauiour his coate, yet he cutt
<pb facs="tcp:1248:7"/>
it not, and as <hi>ſaint Auguſtine</hi> ſayth, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>united it againe with his owne blood. Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in all places againſt all ſpiritts of diuiſion. Shall we heare a diſmall ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of his li. 4. <hi>Contra donatiſtas</hi> Cap. 8. <hi>Constituamus aliquem castum, continentem, non auarum, non idolis ſeruientem, hoſpitalitatem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digentibus miniſtrantem, non cuiuſquam inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, non contentioſum, patientem, quietum, nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li aemulantem, nulli inuidentem, ſobrium, fruga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, ſed haereticum; nulli vtique dubium eſt, propter hoc ſolum quod haereticus est, regnum Dei non poſſeſſurum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If he hath cutt our ſauiour his wholl garment, he hath no shelter for nakednes, no defence againſt gods ſentence of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death.</p>
            <p>And herevpon we ſee, with howe great care haue generall and Prouinciall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells preſently bene conuocated, to cutt of all ſpringing haereſies at their firſt bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. As of <hi>Arius</hi> the <hi>Nicen,</hi> in time of <hi>Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uester.</hi> Of <hi>Macedonius</hi> the firſt <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinopolitan,</hi> in time of <hi>Damaſus.</hi> Of Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius the <hi>Epheſine,</hi> in time of <hi>Celestinus.</hi> Of <hi>Eutyches</hi> the <hi>Calcedon,</hi> vnder <hi>Leo</hi> &amp;c. In
<pb facs="tcp:1248:8"/>
like manner we might deſcend by al cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies. <hi>Oportet quidem haereſes eſſe,</hi> ſaint Paule hath taught vs, there hath bene and will be flawes in the church, but a heauy VAE is adioyned to them that make them. My deſire therefore is, where I ſee any brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches not to ſtretch them ſoe farre till I make them greater, leaſt ſaint Paul his VAE should lay hold on me, rather, if I can ſowe them vp againe, this I conceiue to be <hi>opus ſanctorum.</hi> This hath bene the imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of antiquitie, you knowe <hi>Salomon</hi> adiudged the childe not to be hers, who vnnaturally would haue had it cutt in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that she might haue parte; and the holy ghoſt commends his wiſedome. Howe much more will it argue the church, not to be his mother, who would haue her quartered? <hi>Vnum ouile</hi> ſaith chriſt. Our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour should be to keepe it one; So he left it. The woe lighteth heauily vpon thoſe, who firſt broke it, and much heauier on thoſe who delight in the breach. I find not our beſt Proteſtant diuines to deny many ſaintes to haue bin, euen in latter ages begotten and perfected in the church
<pb facs="tcp:1248:8"/>
of Rome as of ſaint <hi>Thomas of Aquine,</hi> my lord of <hi>Chicheſter</hi> doubteth not to ſtile him ſaint, in his tracte of inuocation of ſaintes. So <hi>Selden de ſucceſsionibus,</hi> ſaint <hi>Anſelme</hi> ſo commonly ſtiled: <hi>S. Bernard, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium calculo,</hi> noe man ſo far callinge his owne iudgment in queſtion, as to doubt of it. Soe doctour <hi>vvhite</hi> againſt <hi>vvhite</hi> dyed blacke; ſo my lord of <hi>Ely</hi> in his fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſermon; my lord of <hi>VVincheſter</hi> in his ſermon of iuſtificacion frequently. <hi>Cauſab:</hi> in his <hi>exercitations.</hi> Whittaker de <hi>eccleſia.</hi> Saint <hi>Francis</hi> by very many, <hi>Pantalion in Cron:</hi> P. 95. ſaith he was a glorious ſaint. <hi>melancthon</hi> with many learned diuines <hi>in corpore doctrinae lypſiae. Saint Bonauenture</hi> ofen ſo intituled by that learned diuine, who put out <hi>Dieta ſalutis</hi> and <hi>Catena aurea</hi> taken out of this learned and pious ſaints greater volumes. Saint <hi>Brigitt</hi> by doctour <hi>Andrevves</hi> againſt <hi>Peron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I could enlarge my ſelfe, but I haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de choyce of theſe more eminent diuines, and thoſe whome our country hath reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced as Illuſtrious Prelats.</p>
            <p>I can not omitt one more <hi>Master Hac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clevvitt</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1248:9"/>
in his booke of Nauigations ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth ſaint <hi>Xauerius</hi> borne in theſe times, in this Centurie, to be a very great ſaint, and diſcribes many particulers of his life.</p>
            <p>I muſt ſtoppe in a ſubiect ſoe obuious. I could wishe and ſo all good men, that there were more departinge chriſtians, ſaints, then to vſe the phraſe of the Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bees, we should haue <hi>more louers of the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, vvho vvould pray much for the people, and</hi> for holy citty.</p>
            <p>That is the church of god; as Iudas found a <hi>Ieremy. Mac.</hi> 2.15.14. for noe doubt in heauen they aſsiſt vs, and by their holy prayers, theſe diuiſions in Religion would be cured, and an vnity concluded.</p>
            <p>Thus far antiquity and, conſent of holy fathers aſſure vs, as all learned Proteſtants agree, and in deed the <hi>creed</hi> declareth it, for there is, <hi>Communio ſanctorum,</hi> a fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship betwixt the triumphant and militant church which, muſt needs be by ſpirituall graces conferred By god vpon vs, by their prayers. So ſaint <hi>Gregorie Nazian: oratione</hi> 18. learnedly explicateth and piouſly
<pb facs="tcp:1248:9"/>
beleeueth. Nay ſaint <hi>Nazianzen</hi> doth not only acknowledge that the ſaints pray for the church in generall, but euen for his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler flocke, as there he ſaith of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed father. Which paſſage of his, I muſt needs ſay, pincheth thoſe who would haue only a generall interceſsion.</p>
            <p>Neither is this all: Antiquity goeth fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſaint <hi>Ambros, To:</hi> 1. <hi>l. de viduis</hi> ſaith, <hi>Obſecrandi ſunt qui nobis ad praeſidium dati ſunt, martyres obſecrandi quorum videmur nobis quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam corporis pignore Patrocinium vindicare, &amp;c.</hi> He ſaith more to the ſame purpoſe there. Neither did I euer read any learned man that doubted this booke to be his, except <hi>Master Perkins</hi> in his problemes, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon, only becauſe there is a booke fathered on him vpon the <hi>Romanes,</hi> wher in the firſt chapter he ſeemeth to teach the contrary. But indeed it is cleare that this booke is not his but one <hi>Hillarius</hi> a <hi>Luciferan</hi> hereticke. I haue read that ſaint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> citeth that booke by the name of one ſaint <hi>Hillarius</hi> how euer it ſeemes ſure not to be his, and the other ſure to be his.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1248:10"/>
               <hi>Saint Hierome</hi> in his funerall oration of <hi>ſaint Paula</hi> ſaith, <hi>vale Paula &amp; cultoris tui vltimam ſenectutem adiuua orationibus.</hi> what can this be called but inuocation, <hi>ſaint Augustine de ciuit:</hi> Li: 21. C: 10. <hi>Vos non martyribus templa ſicut dijs, &amp; ſacrificamus &amp; oramus ſed vtrumque in ordine ad Deum,</hi> ſee how warily and Religiously this great ſaint ſpeakes, he denieth vs to pray to ſaints as to gods, for ſo the gentills obiected againſt chriſtians as is cleare in him and in ſaint <hi>Cyrill</hi> againſt <hi>Iulian</hi> li: 6. yet he gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth expreſly that we pray to them in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to god, which paſſage or diſtinction of his, me thinkes hath ended all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſy betwixte vs.</p>
            <p>So that if any deny this I ſay as <hi>Cauſab:</hi> in his epiſtle to <hi>Bertius de Apoſtaſia ſanctorum, in hoc video nostros docere contraria antiquis pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribus:</hi> for ſurely this is againſt them, and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore my lord of Chicheſter in the aforeſaid tracte (a booke generally receiued in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d) ſtrongly sheweth, voluntary prayer to ſaints, not to be forbidden, and before him, Luther himſelfe in his epiſtle to <hi>Georgius Spalatinus</hi> and <hi>maſter Bilne</hi> as <hi>fox</hi> noteth 462. and others.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1248:10"/>Theſe and many more points of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, are now Ceaſed amongſt the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and indeed, I thinke many more, or all would Ceaſe, if only Learned men should examine them.</p>
            <p>But they muſt not be ſuch who in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of antiquity, can publishe without blushinge a neglecte of the fathers, with <hi>Non ignoro aliter loqui Patres, as Kemnitius</hi> confidently doth. 1. P. <hi>examinus Trid.</hi> or the <hi>Non debetis credere patribus. as Pomecanus</hi> vpon <hi>Ionas.</hi> it is a gudgeon ſoone ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, but not eaſily diſgeſted. For ſurely in the iudgement of the wiſe, it poyſoneth the whole cauſe in hand; if we beleeue <hi>Vincentius Lyrinenſis</hi> in his 40. and 41. CC. yet <hi>Caluin</hi> L. 3. C. 5. Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes them all, and C. 24. exclaimes againſt them for giuing pernicious doctrine of the vncertainty of election: and was not this <hi>Neſtorius</hi> his arrogancy when he ſaw antiquity was againſt him, to bragge that all the doctours before him vnderſtood not ſcripture? as appeares in the councell of <hi>Epheſus:</hi> and yet from him the french diuines haue Learned, not only to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect,
<pb facs="tcp:1248:11"/>
but to brande their gray haires with the note of ſuperſtition; as you may ſee a whole tribe of them in <hi>Feuardentius</hi> in his <hi>Theomachia</hi> L. 11. <hi>de Purgatorio.</hi> Theſe are not they <hi>per quos fiet ſalus in Iſrael.</hi> they are too hott ſpurred and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>prurientes auribus,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetled in their tenents. But milde and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſpiritts may finde the truth, and by them we shall hope for a reconciliation, to which we ſee many of the Learned happily to incline.</p>
            <p>Againe to write the liues of ſaints, and ſo conueigh the memory of their great vertues to poſterity, the holy ſcriptures did it in all the hiſtoricall partes, and <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 24. aduiſeth vs to it, <hi>Sapientiam ipſorum nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent populi, &amp; laudes eorum nuntiet eccleſia,</hi> and it was the practiſe of antiquity. Did not Saint <hi>Gregory Niſſen</hi> write the life of <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Thaumaturgus? Athanaſius</hi> and <hi>Hierome</hi> of Saint <hi>Anthony</hi> the great? <hi>Seuerus Sulpitius</hi> of Saint <hi>Martine?</hi> Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> of Saint <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nett?</hi> Saint <hi>Bonauenture</hi> that great and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout ſcholeman (as <hi>Gerſon</hi> ſtileth him) of Saint <hi>Francis</hi> that ſtupe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dious co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of the world?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1248:11"/>But peraduenture it may be obiected that we are not aſſured this Bleſſed Queene to be a Saint. To this I anſwere, without all queſtion she was a wery holy woman, gaue great teſtimonies of vertue, of the loue of god and her neighbour. And in theſe two are conſummated, both lawes and prophetts; all Chriſtian perfection if we may beleeue our Bleſſed ſauiour. Thus the hiſtories witnes of her; and what is moſt of all, its the eſteeme the whole church of god had of her.</p>
            <p>Which I therfore added, to preuent an obiection (which might be made) of a thiefe, who as it is recorded in Saint <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> his life, was, being dead, eſteemed à Saint, wheras he was indeed a wicked man: and to that text of Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (if it be Saint Auguſtines) <hi>multa corpora Sanctorum venerantur in terris, quorum animae cruciantur in inferno.</hi> Many bodies are reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced on earth, whoſe ſoules are tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in hell.</p>
            <p>But this is by my former clauſe aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſatisfied, for I beleene not that god will permitt the whole church, to erre in
<pb facs="tcp:1248:12"/>
ſo graue a pointe as to take a diuell for a Saint; thoughe particuler churches and prouinces may be deceiued, as all diuines agree, neither did ſaint Auguſtine there intende any more, as <hi>Ambroſius Catharinus Couaruuias</hi> in his <hi>reſolutions</hi> L. 1. C. 10. with Learned <hi>Corduba</hi> in his <hi>queſtionary,</hi> truly expound him: or els you may with <hi>Bellar:</hi> not improbably eſteeme that he meaneth only thoſe, whome the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> reuerenced as their Saints.</p>
            <p>And indeed what wonder if we should attribute ſoe much to the whole church in ſo graue and important a buſines, ſince after others, Learned <hi>Cunaeus</hi> in his <hi>Rep: Iudaeorum</hi> L. 1. C. 12. obſerues out of the <hi>Thalmudiſts</hi> that the Prieſtes in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> had infallible iudgment to decerne an Adultereſſe from the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent: and he addes the reaſon <hi>Sacrum quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam inſtitutum non defuiſſe</hi> 70. <hi>ſenibus, postquam ſolemni actu impoſitae manus illis eſſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus he, grounded vpon gods promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe in Pentateuch to the Synagogue; and can we doubt of the certainty of gods aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance to the church his ſpouſe in decer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:1248:12"/>
falſe and adulterate ſanctity from feigned iuſtice and innocency? is the ſpiritt of god leſſe powerfull, or carefull to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect her in ſo maine a pointe, as to knowe his heauenly gueſtes, from his, and her abiured enemies? or is it leſſe behouefull for her to haue that ſacred inſtinct or tincture of the holy Ghoſte, ſince chriſt his handes were impoſed vpon her ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely on the Croſs? eſpecially in ſoe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious a caſe, as to knowe whether she should celebrate the memory of the dead with thankesgiuing, as antiquity did of martyrs, or with horrour as they did of Apoſtataes and the like? me thinkes the shadowe should not exceed the ſubſtance; hauinge larger promiſes of the directiue ſpiritt of god then they, <hi>Paraclitus docebit omnia.</hi> is it not a good Conſequece, if all, then this? neither doe I thinke my L. of <hi>Couentry</hi> and <hi>Lichfeild</hi> wil find difficulty in this: eſpecially <hi>Theſi.</hi> 2. Fol. 365. ſe. 3. in his grande Impoſture. My Lord of <hi>VVincheſter</hi> deceaſed, plainly held it againſt <hi>Peron</hi> in the end, and ſo doth my Lord of <hi>London</hi> againſt <hi>Foſter.</hi> and ſure I am, Saint
<pb facs="tcp:1248:13"/>
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> would haue preſently ſubſcribed to what the church ſoe generally should haue receiued.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee my grownds (good chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian reader), wherefore I haue peruſed and approued this hiſtory: my finall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue was that we may be incited to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, ſince it is an ornament for Princes Crownes.</p>
            <p>And this is indeed the cheifeſt honour we can giue to ſaints, as ſaint <hi>Nazian: Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione</hi> 18. ſpeaking of Saint <hi>Cyprian.</hi> ſaith, the bleſſed Martir <hi>hoc dedit in mandatis</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by him that his honourers shall be his imitatours <hi>Chrys: ſer.</hi> 1. <hi>de Martir: To.</hi> 3. hath to the ſame purpoſe. Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine ſer.</hi> 47. <hi>de Sanctis, Solemnitates Martyrum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortationes Martyriorum.</hi> the memories and ſolemnities of ſaints, are the inſtructions of ſinners; their liues, our examples. Farewell. Let vs follow Saint <hi>Paule</hi> his counſell, Pray for one another, to be inabled to followe theſe Princely ſteps, this heauenly Kings high way to eternall happines.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1248:13"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY OF ELIZABETH OF HVNGARY.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE was a tyme, when all the fauours of fortune reſted in the family of the kings of Hungary, as all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous Deityes were aſſembled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather in the Pantheon of Rome. It ſeemed shee brake her wings, that shee might not take her flight to any other place, &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke all the powers of the North to become tributary to this Crowne.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1248:14"/>
But in the end the blind creature (not eſteemed a Goddeſſe, but by men who haue noe eyes in their ſoules) turned her backe to the Princes of this houſe, becauſe they would not depart from the ſeruice they had vowed to virtue.</p>
            <p>To iudge of the fall of this houſe by the height thereof, wee muſt reaſcend to this great king of Hungary, to whom in his life time trophyes were erected, &amp; after his death, altars: And from thence deſcend to that young prince who in battell loſt himſelfe with his crowne, &amp; left the fields of Varna perpetuallie dishonoured with the infamy of his defeate.</p>
            <p>But betweene theſe two extrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes there are reckoned vp great felicityes, &amp; among the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable of them, this houſe is renowned for producing Elizabeth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1248:14"/>
a Princeſſe, at this day wayted vpon by Angells in heauen, &amp; ſued vnto by men on earth.</p>
            <p>There are noe perfect beautyes to be found, ſince hee who vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertooke to take the picture of one was inforced to drawe the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell of an hundred different pieces.</p>
            <p>But Elizabeth was faire, and in her all the exquiſite &amp; admirable perfections of her ſexe were ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie.</p>
            <p>The beauty of the ſoule conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth wholly in vertue, that, of the body abſolutely in grace, which dependeth not vpon equall propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of lineaments, &amp; colours of the face, but in a preſence, which tranſporteth, &amp; enforceth the eye to conſider it as a viſible effect, of an inuiſible power of the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Elizabeth was excellent both in the one, and other beyond all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1248:15"/>
but of her ſelfe, to her ſelfe.</p>
            <p>There was nothing ſoe diuine, as her ſoule, nothing ſoe goodly as her ſtature, nothing ſoe royall as her garbe, nothing ſoe beautifull as her face, nothing ſoe amiable as her eyes, nothing ſoe louely as her hart: Louely indeed, but not with loue which is the frenſie of thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghts, the plague of ſoules, a follye inuented by vaine witts, &amp; purſued by idle men; but with that loue wherewith Angells are inflamed, &amp; Saints liue, being the fire of the intellectuall worlde as the Sunne is of the celeſtiall, &amp; the elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie of ours.</p>
            <p>But this being knowne that Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth was admirable in the gifts of minde, and beauty of body, it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth to tell you shee was the daughter of Hungarie; that Fraunce
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1248:15"/>
which adorned heads with the prime crownes of the earth, long time mainteyned that of Hungarie in the houſe of the Earles of Aniou, &amp; that from thoſe Bela the Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father of Elizabeth is deſcended.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bela</hi> the third King of Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie maried Agnes ſiſter of Phillip the ſecond called Auguſtus, or Gods-gift, who eſpouſed Alice of Hungarie: From this mariage iſſued Emerick &amp; Andrew. Ambition which violateth lawes of piety, to mainteyne thoſe of tira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nie, armed An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>drew againſt Emericke, to bereaue him of the crowne which the right of eldership, the lawe of the kingdome, the laſt will of his father had ſett on his head, thinking that though nature had created him ſecond, shee had afforded him courage, &amp; merit enough to goe formoſt.</p>
            <p>God who defendeth kings, who
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1248:16"/>
hath a perticular care of their crownes, &amp; who takes their iuſt quarrells vpon himſelfe, breathed the blaſt of his furie vpon the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes of Andrew. For on the daie of battaile agreed on by the waie of armes, to determine a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, which reaſon could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue, Emerick apeared in the head of his armie, cloathed with royall ornaments bearing on his browe the crowne of the firſt chriſtian king of Hungarie, &amp; with it the diuine character which the finger of God had imprinted on the face of kings as a ray of his diuinity, to make them beloued of the good &amp; feared of the wicked.</p>
            <p>This Hercules (which the Pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies againſt whom hee ſett forward, made appeare much greater) cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his armie to march, not ſoe much to fight, as to triumph.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:1248:16"/>His enemyes; nay rather his mutiniers vnable to continue in the agonyes, and affrightments of their conſciences, and hauing their eyes confounded &amp; exteriourly abashed at the preſence of the lawfull king, rayſed their pikes vpright which they had bent againſt him, layed downe armes, &amp; asked pardon of him from whom they would haue taken the crowne. They abandoned the fortune of Andrew, and ſubmitted to the clemencie of Emerick, who hauing vanquished them without force would haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued them with ſweetnes.</p>
            <p>Hee was not willing to enter into his kingdome, otherwiſe then victorious: eſteeming the virtue ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry miſerable, which is not wayted on by envie, &amp; caytife the fortune that is without enimyes: hee thought not his kingdome happie vnleſſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1248:17"/>
clemencie beganne it, imagining that hee who taketh that, from the heart of a Prince, teareth the altar from the Temple.</p>
            <p>The happy raigne of ſo good a king worthie to haue bene immortall, lasted not aboue eight yeares, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven monethes, &amp; ſixe dayes. <hi>Ladiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus</hi> his ſonne ſucceeded for ſixe-monethes onely. <hi>Andrew</hi> who could not gaine it by force of armes, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued thither by order of ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; was crowned in the great Churche of <hi>Buda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He married <hi>Gertrude</hi> daughter of the Duke of <hi>Morauia, Carinthia,</hi> &amp; <hi>Auſtria. Edwig</hi> his Siſter was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to <hi>Henry</hi> ſurnamed Long-beard, Prince of <hi>Sileſia</hi> &amp; <hi>Polonia.</hi> By this his mariage he had fowre children <hi>Bela, Caloman, Andrew,</hi> &amp; <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> The two firſt came to the Crowne one after another. <hi>Andrew</hi> depriued
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1248:17"/>
by order, &amp; the lawe of birthright from hope of the kingdome, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred vp &amp; downe the world to ſeeke a fortune for himſelfe, &amp; his.</p>
            <p>He reſted at <hi>Venice,</hi> matcht in the houſe of the <hi>Moreſini,</hi> had a ſonne who more couragious then his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that ſtood amuſed in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, (where poppies are not ſuffered to growe one aboue another) came into <hi>Fraunce,</hi> did notable ſeruices for the king, &amp; thoſe of the houſe of <hi>Croy</hi> conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted generall of thir forces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the onely Princeſſe made it appeare in the firſt yeares of her childhood, that she was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen out by heauen to be one of the faireſt flowers, which should on earth receiue the plenitude of its graces. At three yeares of age she was eſpouſed to Lewis ſonne of Herman, Lantsgraue of <hi>Heſſe</hi> &amp;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1248:18"/>
               <hi>Thuringia,</hi> who was ſaid to diſcend from <hi>Charlemayne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Promiſes were made with great ceremonie to honour her who knewe not what it was, and, who knowing it, made no more accompt of it, then the winde to breake a rush. At fower yeares of age she was led towards her eſpousalls, by the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours of the king her father, &amp; ſpent the yeares of her childhood in the exerciſe of piety, whereby, they might make a true eſtimate of the reſt of her future life. It is a ſingular furtherance, &amp; notable meanes for a princeſſe well borne, to receiue &amp; learne the precepts of carriage from the hands of her mother; but <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> taken awaie ſo young into the houſe of a ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, was depriued of this happineſſe.</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding she was there bred ſutablie to the greatneſſe of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1248:18"/>
the place from whence she came, &amp; to the excellencie of her wit she then learned that, (the ignorance whereof proues ill for a Princeſſe, who hath thoughts beyond the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaffe, &amp; needle of ordinarie wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) &amp; knewe thoſe things, wherein many great Princeſſes of that name became ſo excellent, that they tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght even kings themſelues to liue.</p>
            <p>Though she were yong, she made her ſelfe deafe &amp; indocible to all diſcourſe, but of heaven; she could not be drawne out of Churches, beginning early to purify her heart from all earthly thoughts, as gould is cleanſed from droſſe of the mine. Then did her gouerneſſe tell her the world was not worthy of her, that she was not made for the world, that her loue not vnlike the ſupreame eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſuffered not by Vapours, nor thoſe infectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which corrupt others.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:1248:19"/>When she was of riper yeares she framed vnto her ſelfe a rule of life wholly pious and deuout, nor was it by precedent or imitation, as there are many, who haue noe other touch of vertue, and piety then conformity of example; but vpon her owne choyce, &amp; the mere motion of the grace of God.</p>
            <p>Her exerciſe was entirely reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious ſo ſoone as she awaked, the firſt thought her ſoule admitted, &amp; which ſwayed throughout the whole day, was the remembrance of death; then ryſing out of bed, she repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vnto her ſelfe the comfort, &amp; infinite ioy of thoſe, who at the ſound of the trumpet shall riſe againe to glory.</p>
            <p>As many pieces of attire as she putt on, ſo many vertues wished she, for the beauty and ornament of her ſoule. When she was cloathed,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1248:19"/>
she proſtrated her ſelfe at the feete of a Crucifixe, renewing the homage of her heart to the goodneſſe of God, giuing thankes for his benefitts, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring his mercy for her ſinnes, &amp; his holy ſpiritt for her direction, proteſting rather to dy, then to looſe his fauour, the very life of her life.</p>
            <p>As in the morning she meditated on that she was to doe, ſoe in the euening she required an account of her ſoule, of what she had done; she often fed it with the bleſſed Sacrament, the bread of Angells, the Manna of heauen, the reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue of life, the ſoueraine remedy againſt death, the admirable proofe of the loue of God towards men; Who notwithſtanding in ſtead of yeilding him thankes for ſo great a benefitt receiued, do now diſpute, whether it be true that he gaue it.</p>
            <p>All the day long she ſtood vpon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1248:20"/>
her guard againſt the ſubtile ſnares of the world, from which she ſought to diſengage her ſelfe; she auerted her eyes aſwell as her thoughts from all illuſions, keeping her ſelfe very carefullie from taſting the honey of pleaſures &amp; vanityes of Court, more daungerous then that which bewitcheth men. If at any tyme she approached, it was but as the fly, which buzzeth about, &amp; feares to reſt vpon it, leaſt he looſe his wings.</p>
            <p>The marriage treated in her child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood was confirmed at ſuch tyme as diſcretion made her capable of choice, or refuſall: but it was done with ſo much coldneſſe, that many thought, if she had not imagined, the diſpoſe of her body was due to her father, shee no whit had feared to diſobey him, to purſue the holy inſpirations, which she now intertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of continuing a virgin.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:1248:20"/>Of three conditions of the femi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine ſexe, there is not any one whoſe contentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hath not anxiety. If marriage haue fruitfullnes, it hath alſo corruption; If widowhood enioy liberty, it likewiſe ſuffers the ſadnes of ſolitude: If virginity put on inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, it liueth with the griefe of ſterility. But <hi>Elizabeth</hi> better loued to liue a virgin then a mother, and hauing dedicated all her thoughts to virginity, she held it ſacriledge to employ them on marriage; well remembring that many of her qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity had gone out of the pallaces of kings their fathers; not being able to preſerue this flower, among the thornes, &amp; bryars of worldlie vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, &amp; the nipping froſts of its impietyes.</p>
            <p>Tranſported then by two ſo powerfull lawes, the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, &amp; authority of her
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1248:21"/>
father, she gaue conſent to this match. The Landtsgraue brought with him as many graces as he acknowledged &amp; admired in her: she likewiſe afforded him ſo much affection, that neuer were two hearts ſcorched with more ardent flames. It was thought her marriage mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght cut of ſomething of the firſt ſeuerity of her life, and that she would begin to relish the pleaſures of youth. But her heart, like a lampe perpetuallie burning before the face of God, shined not at all in the darknes of the brighteſt ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of the day. Her eyes were wearie in behoulding things ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, her eares diſpleaſed with harmonious, her taſt with the moſt delicious, but her heart was neuer ſatiated with the loue of God.</p>
            <p>This her triangle could neuer
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1248:21"/>
bee filled, but by this triangle. She ſtole the ſweeteſt houres of the night from repoſe, to ly at the foote of the Croſſe, &amp; taſt the bitternes thereof in the ſecurity of ſilence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sophia</hi> her mother in lawe, &amp; <hi>Agnes</hi> her ſiſter in lawe coniured her to forſake her ſcrupuloſity; And will you Madame (ſaid they) perpetuallie vſe your ſelfe ſo cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly? Will you alwaies preferre thornes before roſes? Will you be ſo sharp an enemy to your ſelfe, as to hasten your death at the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me when you ought to thinke vpon life? Since life is ſo short, that if the world be not ſeaſonablie vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, wee dy before wee knowe it.</p>
            <p>Her ſilence anſweared for her, and her conſtant perſeuerance gaue them occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to iudge what they mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght hope from such diſcourſe. She co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1248:22"/>
this kinde of life amidſt all theſe impertinences; but auoided thoſe deuotions, more faigned then holy, which ſeeme to tranſport into extaſy the mindes of thoſe which vſe them to pleaſe the world, &amp; to ſatisfy their owne hipocriſy. They are ſtarres neither ſtable, nor fixed, in the firmament of true piety, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wandring fires, Comets, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halations of the earth, which diſſolue into the ayre of vanity.</p>
            <p>The Court of this Princeſſe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe reſembled not thoſe, which were at that tyme ſaid to be ſeas of diſſolution, and which, as the Sea, were ſwolne vp with pride, foaming with exorbitance, &amp; where vertue was perpetuallie in torment. Hers was a temple of piety, an Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demy of honour: her example per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumed the moſt corrupted ayre, and breathed into the moſt wauering
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1248:22"/>
affections firme thoughts of virtue: with one glaunce of her eye, she led the reſt along, and withdrew them from errour, which inticeth heartes to pleaſure, hath its carreere of Ice, &amp; in the end a precipice.</p>
            <p>Her ladyes and maides were bred without curioſity, vanity, or nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; Their eyes by a modeſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine mortifyed euill appetites. And becauſe the beſt borne natures by deprauation become worſe then others (as the corruption of good things is worſt of all) she had an infinite care this firſt integrity might neuer be diſſolued. For which cauſe she exhorted them to hold the heart in liberty, the body in ſeruitude, and the conſcience in repoſe; aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them of the infinite content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they should one day haue, in ſeeing their ſowles in heauen free from slaunder, &amp; leauing their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1248:23"/>
on the earth without infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</p>
            <p>She recommended nothing ſo much vnto them, as to ſtifle wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thoughts in their birth; whileſt the bramble is greene it may be eaten, but when it becomes big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, it choketh. When the ſpirit is caught in thoſe firſt perſwaſions of loue, it reſembleth the bird, which intangleth her ſelfe the more she fluttereth &amp; ſtriues to be at liberty. How many tymes did she tell them, the ſuits of men were to be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected? that they were coales either burning, or que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ched, &amp; that the leaſt we might expect from them was either to enflame, or beſmeare: That the Panther was not ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſtrangled in taſting <hi>Aconite,</hi> then the Soule of a woman by harkning to the diſcourſe of a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate louer.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:1248:23"/>There are of them (ſaid she) who boaſt to vnderſtand without yielding, &amp; to heare not delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in what is ſayed. If they be quick to deſire, they are very reſerued in making their deſires knowne, they mocke at thoſe, who haue neither eyes, nor eares to ſee or vnderſtand ſuch, as conſpire againſt their honour vnder the sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of affection. But the opinion they haue of their owne ſtrength is a falſe gate, a drowſie ſentinell which betrayeth, &amp; ſuffers reaſon to be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed. Ladies of this diſpoſition ought to ſee them ſelues in the eye &amp; fortune of others, and to belieue that which hath happen<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ed is nor im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to them, ſince they floate in the like Sea, &amp; are toſſed with the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me winde, &amp; waues. And though they thinke their veſſell ſtronger, &amp; much better appointed, yet may the ſtorme
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1248:24"/>
perhaps be more violent, the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt more terrible, &amp; the waues ſoe redoubled, that not knowing how to make reſiſtance, they may be inforced to yeild vp their frai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght to the tempeſt.</p>
            <p>Implacable enemy of vice! she would neuer looke on thoſe, who ſo much regarded the beauty of the body, to deforme that of the ſoule; natures ready, &amp; apt for ill, ſtupid to good; that wound with eyes, deceyue with the tongue, and who are inforced by remorſe of their conſciences to become pale with griefe, ruddy with shame in good company; who (impudent as they are) ſett that to ſale, which admitts noe price, nor commerce in Soules that hold honour for the fift element of their life, &amp; laſtly who haue ſworne to this falſe opinion, that the lawe, which obligeth a woman
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1248:24"/>
to loue but one man, is not made for thoſe, whoe are worthy to be loued of many.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the greatneſſe of her quality, &amp; the condition of Court permitted not this Princeſſe to be perpetuallie for her ſelfe, to be euer retired, inceſſantly ſpeaking to God, or hearing God ſpeake, to her; yet did not her hart indure, that any should enioy her to preiudice the comfort &amp; contentment of her minde.</p>
            <p>If ſometimes the Landtsgraue needs would open his heart to giue paſſage to penſiue imaginations, &amp; to that end imployed the charmes of muſicke, it was but in ſinging ſome holy poëme.</p>
            <p>But in midſt of moſt ordinarie ſollaces her heart perpetuallie tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned towards the North of the croſſe, her minde reſted in the tranquillity
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1248:25"/>
of her thoughts; This muske ceaſed not to ſmell ſweetly, euen in places leaſt ſauouring of piety. She neuer appeared in publique with orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſutable to a Princeſſe, of ſo noble &amp; high extraction, that she promiſed not her ſoule, to auenge it in conuenient tyme at the charge of her body, for all theſe vanityes.</p>
            <p>Entring one day into the Church, vpon ſome ſolemnity which by the cuſtome of the world permitted her not to be otherwiſe ſeene then well attired, caſting her eyes vpon the Crucifixe, she ſayed to her ſelfe; muſt my head ſparkle with diamonds &amp; pretious ſtones, my fingers with rings, &amp; I behold on this croſſe the head of my Sauiour crowned with thornes, and his hands pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with nayles? Then proſtrating her ſelfe on the earth, she beſought God to doe her the fauour she
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1248:25"/>
might intermingle the acerbityes of the Croſſe with all the felicityes the world could affoord her.</p>
            <p>She knew heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was to be opened with two keyes; the one of gould, which is prayer; the other of iron which is affliction: she carryed them both all the dayes of her life. Prayer was continuallie hanging on her tongue, &amp; she euer hanging on the Croſſe. The image of our lady of Hall neare Bruſſells came from her deuotion, &amp; it is ſaid, was brought thether by <hi>Sophia</hi> her daughter mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed to <hi>Henry</hi> the 2. Duke of <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As she was indefatigable in prayer, ſo was she inuincible in afflictions: for her courage went before them: she held them as Embaſſages ſent from Heauen; she receiued them anſwerable to the greatneſſe &amp; Maieſty of such a Monarch of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1248:26"/>
world, on whom all the earth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth who ill intreateth an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour, plainely diſcouereth a neglect of the Prince, that ſent him.</p>
            <p>The life, which taſteth noe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions is a dead Sea, which produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth nothing. The Soule not viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is as abandoned by the Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian. The land where perfect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of minde groweth, is plou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghed vp by the share of torments, ſowed with ashes, watered with tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res &amp; hedged round about with thornes. And although she abode in the delights of the world, she no more taſted of them, then the fish of the Seas brackishneſſe. The brighteſt dayes ſeemed duskie ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghts to her being rightly inſtructed, that he who will weare Coronets of flowers in this world, beareth thoſe of thornes in the other, &amp; he
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1248:26"/>
who ſoweth ſorrowes in this life shall reape comforts.</p>
            <p>Her nature was too generous, and too good not to reſent the cruell, &amp; tragicall death of the Queene of <hi>Hungary</hi> her mother, who was ſlayne by a hand furiouſly tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with iealouſy &amp; reuenge, which drenching the Court in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable amazement, made her ſee, that by how much the more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent the heates are, ſoe much the more impetuous are the windes; great afflictions fall vpon great proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perities.</p>
            <p>It was in the tyme when all Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope ſtretched out a benigne arme to Chriſtians, ſurcharged &amp; oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in <hi>Soria</hi> by the armes of Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dells. The God of Hoſtes had giuen two blowes in fauour of the trueth of religion. One in Spaine againſt the Moores, who loſt at the battell
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1248:27"/>
of <hi>Nauas</hi> two hundred thouſand men aſtonished vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſight of the Croſſe borne by the Archbiſchop of <hi>Tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledo,</hi> who marched in the front of the Chriſtian army: The other a yeare after this in Fraunce againſt the <hi>Abbigenſes,</hi> that were defeated with the Count of <hi>Tholouſe</hi> their leader, &amp; the king of <hi>Arragon</hi> their protectour.</p>
            <p>Theſe two victories obtayned, animated the Chriſtian Princes to ſeeke out the common enemy at home, &amp; to caſt the fire of warre into the entrayles of his Empire. For which purpoſe, the Croiſaide was reſolued on &amp; decreed in the councell of <hi>Lateran,</hi> one of the greateſt &amp; moſt eminent Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyes that euer hath been in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome: for beſides the Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours from all Princes, there were two Patriarkes, ſeauenty Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1248:27"/>
foure hundred and twelue Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, eight hundred other prelates.</p>
            <p>Firſt the zeale to the ſeruice of God, &amp; next the compaſſion of the miſeryes, which Chriſtians ſuffered in <hi>Soria</hi> obliged Chriſtian Princes to haſten to their ayde, ſince Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants draw their fellowes out of the ditch, &amp; Gilt-heads free their companions from ſnares.</p>
            <p>Deſire of glory &amp; reputation which is the ſpurre wherwith theſe lyon-like hearts awaken, and doe incite their generous ſpirits, ſtirred vp the moſt religious princes to carry the Croiſaide, eſteeming it no leſſe glory to raiſe the tropheys of the croſſe on the frontiers of <hi>Egipt,</hi> then did <hi>Alexander</hi> by er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecting two altars in the vtmoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of the Indyes, &amp; <hi>Hercules</hi> two pillars on the bounds of his naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:1248:28"/>It was deſired this enterpriſe might haue a Commander capable for the conduct of a roiall army, and to returne victorious. <hi>Andrew</hi> king of <hi>Hungary,</hi> &amp; <hi>Tranſiluania</hi> by a common conſent was choſen out for this charge, which he accepted with that content, wherewith the heartes of great Princes are euer poſſeſſed when they meete with oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, which free them from pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity or corriuallship with others. It could not fall into better hands although in the purſuites of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition great honours willingly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt to thoſe, who goe ſloweſt, as the Hart many tymes yields him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the man, that leaſt chaſed him.</p>
            <p>Hauing then taken away all affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions from his owne will, to become obedient to that, which God diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered vnto him by this election,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1248:28"/>
he muſtred all the forces of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and thereunto added thoſe of his neighbours, to ioyne with the Chriſtian Army at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> He left the Princes his ſonnes vnder the charge of the Queene his wife, &amp; indeed all of them together vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the prudence &amp; fidelity of the Count of <hi>Bankban,</hi> whom hee made Lieutenant Generall in high, &amp; low <hi>Hungary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His abſence cauſed great griefe in his Court, but the arriuall of the prince brother to the Queene ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them, that ſo they might be ſeaſoned with a ſtrange bitterneſſe. He was of an age wherein luſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to warre againſt vertue, &amp; where with Hercules was forcibly aſſailed by attraction of the one, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the other. His heart was a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe which as yet had neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued garriſon, hee hauing preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1248:29"/>
it in the firſt liberty of its birth-Loue ſurpriſed it by gayning the eyes, which were the ſentinells.</p>
            <p>He ſawe among the Ladies of Court attending on the Queene his ſiſter the Counteſſe of <hi>Banckban:</hi> He iudged her the faireſt, &amp; found her one of the wiſeſt: Her beauty was not an vncomly hoſteſſe in an hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome houſe; For she obeyed vertue which held it in propriety, &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles fell into diſcord with her honour. Loue againſt her liking &amp; with out her conſent made vſe of her eyes, for all manner of artille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. They were fires to burne, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes to wound, burning mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours to turne the veſſells of thoſe into cinders, who vndertooke to ſayle on this ſea of the Courte, &amp; loue. Yet neuer durſt he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt this <hi>Minerua,</hi> it being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to finde her idle. The prince
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1248:29"/>
who ever had beene for him ſelfe, was now for her, ſo ſoone as euer he beheld her.</p>
            <p>This paſſion forcing with its vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, thoſe things which cannot be inforced, commaunded its liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to manifeſt its ſeruitude. He thought himſelfe too couragious not to tell her of it, &amp; her too cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous not to hearken to it. Princes, though all things ſtand faire for them, are not free from trouble in theſe firſt circumſtances; for indee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de they thinke ceremonies are not made, but for ſuch as are on equall termes; if they vſe them, they vould haue them accounted an ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour, that their intreatyes may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, &amp; that noe fauour be ſo great, which they muſt not buy at a coſtly rate.</p>
            <p>The torment of the prince which should be leſſe cruell diſcouered,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1248:30"/>
then concealed, redoubled the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence there of, ſo ſoone as his ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue had vnfolded to the Counteſſe the euill which his eyes had done to his heart. For this firſt view, which was but a ſingle deſire became all loue, &amp; by theſe approaches, he tourned into fury, &amp; an vniuſt conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piracy againſt her honour.</p>
            <p>The Counteſſe in ſtead of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting the power which the Prince offered her ouer his heart, made it appeare vnto him she neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded his ſuite, nor affection, though it were the moſt ardent, which true loue might tender to a heart well beloued, and that hers could not receiue any impreſſion, then of the lawfull loue of her husband.</p>
            <p>The Prince meeting with ſuch &amp; ſoe couragious reſiſtance, &amp; deſpayring to ouercome this reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion diſcouered to his Siſter all the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1248:30"/>
woundes of his ſoule, found noe comfort but in her affection, who shewed her ſelfe not inſenſible of his torment.</p>
            <p>We haue often ſeene ſeruants, who haue betrayed their Miſtreſſes, but it is a prodigious thing, when we behould ſeruants betrayed by their miſtreſſes. Shee conſpired in fauour of the Prince her Brother againſt the honour of the Counteſſe, and promiſed him to gaine her to his deſire, either by loue or force.</p>
            <p>The next enſueing night the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy was executed, the body van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished the heart inuincible. There was but one night betweene this iniury, &amp; the reuenge, which, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported the Count of <hi>Banckban</hi> in to ſuch furie, that earlie in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning he ſtab'd his dagger into the boſome of the Queene, who had bee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a bad Miſtreſſe to be a good Siſter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:1248:31"/>Heere it is where humane iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt ſtrike ſayle, and caſt it ſelfe into the vaſt Ocean of thoſe of the liuing God, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of which, the moſt cleare ſeeing eyes are Owles in the rayes of the ſunne.</p>
            <p>Of one ſame mother were borne two Siſters, Gertrude, who turned away from the feare &amp; loue of God, &amp; Hedwige, whoſe life was ſo reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished with piety, &amp; adorned with ſo many vertues, that she hath beene canonized for a Saint; Sorro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes violent &amp; vnexpected are not for ſimple diſcourſes. Thoſe are not great which can be expreſſed. This accident by ſome eſteemed parricide, by others iuſtice, offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded &amp; ſcandalized the whole Court, &amp; layed incurable woundes on the Sowle of the Princeſſe Elizabeth, but she for all that murmured
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1248:31"/>
not againſt God, whoſe wiſedome she adored with all humility, hauing her eye in this mishap, noe more troubled, then her heart.</p>
            <p>Time and patience, which cure all diſturbances nourished, &amp; gaue increaſe to hers</p>
            <p>Shee not ſo much reflected on the death of the body, as she entred into ſtrange apprehenſions for the health of the Soule.</p>
            <p>The Count of Banckban hauing ſett the affaires of the kingdome in good order, his wife &amp; Family into ſafegard, went to Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople to caſt himſelfe at the feete of the king, making him both iudge &amp; auenger of the fact, which hee confeſſed to haue committed by a powerfull inſtigation, &amp; for the which he at the leaſt much repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him.</p>
            <p>Teares haſtned in ayde of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1248:32"/>
the words, which ſorrowe ſtopped in his breaſt.</p>
            <p>Yet for all this, amazement could not ſeyze on the kings heart, If he in middeſt of armes shedd teares, to vapour out his griefe by them the ſorrowe to haue loſt a good wife &amp; his children a good mother, would make them to powre them out in aboundance.</p>
            <p>He patiently heard the Count of Banckban and prudently, aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that at his returne he would vnderſtand the trueth of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; That thoſe who are preſent neuer want excuſes, &amp; the abſent euer ſuffer wrong. That he would heare his brother in lawe &amp; the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes of his wife. He ſent him backe againe to continue his ſeruice. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uinced by his ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne confeſſion, &amp; that ſoe ſtraunge an act required ſome exemplar punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1248:32"/>
yet hee would not dishonour the happy beginnings of his voya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, by acts of ſuch ſeuerity, nor leaue the army to retourne into Hungary.</p>
            <p>The rendeuous was in Cyprus, all the shippes arriued there: It was aduiſed on what ſide the enemy should be aſſayled.</p>
            <p>Particulier intereſt entreth into conſultation with the principall of them. The king of Cyprus deſires it may be vpon on ſide, He of Ieruſalem hath deſignes vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>The king of Hungary that knewe a Generall of an army ought to haue eyes in his shoulders, to leaue nothing behind, which might hinder him to proceede any further, was of opinion the fortreſſe of Mount Thabor should bee beſieged. The Count of Tripoly diuerteth this
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1248:33"/>
reſolution &amp; cauſed the Army to march before Damiatta, hauing firſt attempted to ſurpriſe the Fort of <hi>Thabor,</hi> where blowes were giuen and taken at ſo ſmall a diſtance, that the Infidells might ſee, not onely flyes, but euen the little Croſſes, which were vpon the Chriſtians Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getts.</p>
            <p>The king of Hungary ſeeing the enterpriſes were mannaged without iudgement, &amp; that priuate paſſions ouerthrewe the beſt Counſells in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the publique good; that the moſt valiant ſtood more in neede of a Buckler, then a ſworde, grewe into diſtaſt, and hauing left among the knights of <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> great proofes of his bounty, as hee from them had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of their valour &amp; affection, hee returned into <hi>Europe,</hi> &amp; left the charge of his army to thoſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1248:33"/>
who reſembled the prouince in which they fought, exteriourly hott, as being one of the neareſt to the torrid Zone, &amp; within extreamely cold.</p>
            <p>After a ten monthes ſiege the Chriſtian army entred <hi>Damiata,</hi> the firſt Standard which appeared on the wall was that of <hi>Florence,</hi> which at that tyme was a white lilly in a red field. The Conquerors for all their booty found nothing, but ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of bloud, &amp; heapes of the dead; for of ſeauenty thouſand who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended this Citty there were rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned vp, but three thouſand mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger diſcomfited Creatures, that looked like frightnig Ghoſtes.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtians kept not this Citty ſo long tyme as they had ſpent in taking it: For beſieging <hi>grand Cairo,</hi> in the ſeaſon when Nilus ouer floweth, they ſawe them
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1248:34"/>
ſelues ſoe aſſayled by waters, that their victuall &amp; munition being drowned, they could finde no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fety, but in a happy compoſition to depart, &amp; yeild vp <hi>Damiata.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>Nilus</hi> tooke from them all meanes to drawe neare to the towne, ſo the <hi>Sultan of Egipt</hi> cut them of from all paſſages of retreate. Thoſe, who heretofore commaunded with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out condition are inforced to receiue lawe of the enemy, who left them noe other fruit of their conqueſt, but the shame not to bee able to keepe what they had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</p>
            <p>The king of <hi>Hungary,</hi> who could not triumph ouer his enemyes in the holy land, ſerued as a Trophey to the Princeſſe of <hi>Ferrara:</hi> For paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing through this Citty to <hi>Venice,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Inſprucke,</hi> he ſawe in her, perfections of beauty
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1248:34"/>
ſo admirable, &amp; wonders of loue ſo abſolute, that hee ſubmitted all his affections to her power. His eyes had no other obiect, his fantaſy no other imagination, his minde no other diſcourſe, his heart no other conference, his mouth no other name, then of the Princeſſe. His memory was ſo replenished with her meritt, that it noe longer would admitt any thoughts of the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall death of his firſt wife.</p>
            <p>Hee vnfolded his heart vnto her; Saying, his affection was ſuch, that hee was wholly vnable to ſtirre any further, but to enioy the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of her company. Kings are neuer refuſed; Hee ſpake of it to the marqueſſe of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> and intreated he would giue him the Princeſſe his daughter to ſucceede, not to the vnhappineſſe, but to the dignity of <hi>Gertrude</hi> his firſt wife.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1248:35"/>
Hearts conſenting, bodyes were quickly vnited, &amp; the King of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> entred into his kingdome, with the ſole triumph of the loue, &amp; beauty of a worthy Princeſſe.</p>
            <p>The firſt act after his mariage, and returne, was the proceſſe againſt the Count of <hi>Banckban.</hi> The opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Counſell being better pondered, then reſolued, hee was freed, but in ſuch ſort, that the reſt of his life was to him but a liuing death; for thoſe who either through duty &amp; affection were obliged to the memory, &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Queene proſecuted him in his perſon, his fortune, and his family as an execrable parricide, yea euen they, who had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the king neuer to ſearch any further into the matter, redoubled their proſecution, thinking oathes might be broken without periury,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1248:35"/>
and benefitts forgotten without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, to maynteyne points of honour.</p>
            <p>The king, who for the loue of the liuing had allmoſt blotted out the memorie of the dead, diſpoſed his thoughts to congratulations of ioy vpon the Queenes entrance into his capitall Citty of <hi>Bude,</hi> which was at that tyme the theater of Northern magnificence, a City faire rich &amp; great, bearing the ſurname of Attilaes brother, who cauſed it to be built on the banck of <hi>Danu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ioy which ſoe puffed vp many hearts, shrunck vp with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the heart of the Princeſſe <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who was ſent for by the king her father to entertayne the Queene, and to augment by her preſence the comfort of his retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne from the Eaſtern warres. Shee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1248:36"/>
her ſelfe, &amp; accommodated the temper of her countenance to the humours, &amp; contentments of the king her father, but in ſecret she ſtill had in ſtore new teares to bewayle this old griefe for the death of her mother.</p>
            <p>It is not vntruely ſayd, that one ſorrowe ordinarily ſerues as a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine for an other; she ſtayed not long in <hi>Marpurg,</hi> but returned thence to meete the Landtsgraue her husband, at which tyme her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy was aſſayled by a newe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction.</p>
            <p>Death iealous of the long peace, and concord of their mariage, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired with fortune to ſeparate them, and not daring to vndertake it without the helpe of vertue, they agreed to adde an occaſion, in the purſuite whereof it was more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to dye, then to liue in diſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:1248:36"/>All <hi>Europe</hi> was terrifyed with the happy ſucceſſe of the Infidell ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in <hi>Egipt.</hi> The Emperour <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick Barbaroſſa,</hi> who had maryed the daughter of the king of <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> was humbly beſought &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated togeather with all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes to ſuccour the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. He appointed a great part of them to meete at <hi>Cremona,</hi> there to aduiſe vpon meanes to ſecure the affaires of Chriſtendome againſt the attempts of Pagans, and to Saue <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> from their tiranny. All ſayed they muſt haſten thither but fewe were willing to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in ſoe perilous, and tedious a voyage. The Landtsgraue anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them all to ſoe holy a warre, and offered himſelfe to followe the Emperour thither. He was reputed able to leade the wholl Armye, &amp; to be Generall of it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:1248:37"/>The king of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> preſſed ſo much to haue it ſett forward, leaſt delay might render it vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, that the La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dtsgraue being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to depart, had not leiſure to returne into <hi>Thuringia,</hi> prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the aduancement of the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que cauſe before his owne affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The adieu which hee ſent by wryting to the Princeſſe <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his wife, ſerued him then for a voyage into the other world.</p>
            <p>The army was muſtered at <hi>Brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſi,</hi> where the Emperour fell ſicke. It was aſſaulted by ſo many ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and tempeſts, that diuers ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed for the returne of it into Europe. The Landtsgraue cauſed the chiefe of them to aſſemble to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather, to lett them knowe it was more shamefull to retire backe, then perilous to paſſe on. Hee ſpake to them in this manner: The tyme
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1248:37"/>
(Sirs) wee looſe in conſulting vpon our returne, will condemne vs of cowardize if wee paſſe noe further. Words are vnneceſſary, when there is queſtion, not to liue, but to march on. I lead not fresh-water ſouldiers: paſſed daungers ought to make theſe to be ſcorned, which are before vs; More glory may be found in the trueth of that, which wee nowe are, then in the vanity of what wee haue beene. Wee are not vpon the Sea, but to goe on couragiouſly in the face of death, when it is preſented; and to expect it with a firme conſtancye. Followe me, for you shall neuer beare the firſt brunt, nor will I withdrawe my ſelfe from daungers, to thruſt you vpon them.</p>
            <p>All with geſtures, vowes, and voyces ſeconded the braue exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the Landtsgraue, &amp; every
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1248:38"/>
one proteſted either to leaue his head in <hi>Aſia,</hi> or to returne with it into <hi>Europe</hi> crowned with lawrel, not any of them but much deſired to gather the Palmes, which <hi>Pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> produceth.</p>
            <p>But this firſt feruour became a groſſe ſurge of ſmoake, which va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished in an inſtant: For the army being ready to aſſault, ſawe it ſelfe aſſayled by a malady, winch conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly diſpread thoroughout all the Nations and ſeuerall bands. The Emperour <hi>Frederik</hi> grew very ſicke, and the voyage abſolutely fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</p>
            <p>The Landtsgraue dyed there and with him the hope of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to aduaunce the triumphs of <hi>Godfrey of Boulon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hee dyed for griefe to behould his hopes ſtopped in the middeſt of their carreere. Falſe hopes of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:1248:38"/>
the worlde They lift men vp like young Children to the braunch of a Tree and in an inſtant take their shoulders away, which ſupported them, and leaue them hanging in the ayre. Hee commaunded his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be layed in the tombe of his Aunceſtors in <hi>Thuringia,</hi> and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got nothing neceſſarie for the good of his eſtate. His memory and iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being vigorous to ſett all in order, made it appeare, that thoſe neglect not them ſelues in death, who forget not God in their life.</p>
            <p>The newes of his death was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly caryed to the Princeſſe <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> who found her ſelfe drenched in an Abiſſe of ſorrowes, when she read thoſe expreſſe dead wordes of the liuely affection of the Landts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue, written by him a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death, in theſe termes.</p>
            <p>Madame, I am not in a condition
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1248:39"/>
eyher to counterfet, or diſguiſe my thoughts, ſince ſo little tyme is left me to render them pure and ſincere to him, who knowes them. Liuing with you the deare moity of my ſelfe, I haue deſired nothing ſo much, as the ſtudy of trueth, nor will I admitt that my end con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict my life: to giue you aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that as I haue not ſought to preſerue it but for you, ſoe it trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles me not to dye, but abſented from you. The Sunne shewes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe more luſtrous when hee ſetts, the loue I beare you was neuer more perfect, then in the period of the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident of my life, which openeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee the day-breake of immortal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. Farewell (ſweeteſt); I should grieue for the ſorrowe you will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertayne, did I not knowe you haue wherewithall to defend your vertue from the outrages of fortune.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:1248:39"/>Lo, a ſtroke of dolour and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which shooke, but overthrewe not the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> God was pleaſed the temptation should not exceede the power of her reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Her good nature hauing powred out a torrent of teares of ſorrowe, her heart afforded on Ocean of ioy, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the Landtsgraue was freed from the miſeryes of life more brittle then glaſſe, lighter then ſmoake, ſwif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter farre and more empty, then the winde. Then lifting vp her hands, &amp; eyes to heauen, she gaue God than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes for this afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by which he had reſtored her to the liberty she ſo much deſired, to be wholly conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to his ſeruice.</p>
            <p>Nowe it is (o lord) nowe is the tyme (ſaid she) that I with more liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will wayte on thee, behold me free, that I may forſake theſe lower playnes, and with alacrity aſcend
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1248:40"/>
vp to Mount <hi>Thabor.</hi> Behold me diſcharged from that, which was moſt deare vnto me in this life, I haue nothing elſe to looſe, &amp; who knowes whether I had not been vndone, without this loſſe.</p>
            <p>The comforts of her mariage, and the greatneſſe of her condition had not at all extinguished in her the true contentments shee propoſed to her ſelfe in a priuate, and ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie life. Shee often ſayed, her husband was the flower of the field, that could not be found in Cityes. That the Temple of repoſe was built in the Suburbes. That the honey of the Soule was made in the hyue of ſolitude.</p>
            <p>This death brought that life to her, which she deſired, and that she might wholly and entirely vowe her ſelfe to it, she diſarrayed her ſelfe from all pleaſures of the world. she
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1248:40"/>
gaue to Churches, Colledges and Hoſpitalls, all which she in her Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet had of moſt price: much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re eſteeming the charity of almes then the guift of miracles, becauſe (ſayd she) man is bound to God by miracles, and God to men by almes. She cheerefullie gaue, not with a countenance denying what she had preſented. She gaue ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, neither wearying patience, nor intreatyes. Teares (ſayd she) which auayle little with men, are very powerfull with God, to gayne hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            <p>Shee daily fed nine hundred poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re people, and this largeſſe was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted prodigality by thoſe, who iudged her deuotion to be hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, her zeale and humility, groſſe folly. <hi>Henry</hi> Brother of <hi>Lewis</hi> hearing of his death, ſeized on the fortreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and banished the Princeſſe, who
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1248:41"/>
found no retreate: ſo much the feare to diſpleaſe the ſtrongeſt, and awe of the moſt powerfull doeth over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſway affections.</p>
            <p>She went to a Church and there cauſed the Canticle of triumph, &amp; ioy to be ſung, for the fauour which God had done, by ſetting her into a Courſe of life, that she by the lawe of her condition expected not, hauing euer deſired pouerty without hope to attayne it.</p>
            <p>Yet for all that, she loſt not the generoſity of her birth; Riches could not make a Coward of the valiant, nor pouerty a magnanimous heart, to become ſordid; for shee was not ashamed at all, but of thoſe who liued ill, and of ſuch as were onely poore againſt their wills.</p>
            <p>Fortune coulde not take that away which she gaue her not. The greatneſſe of her courage is exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1248:41"/>
&amp; continueth greene among iniuryes, as Iuy in ruines.</p>
            <p>She perſiſted in this patience till the arriuall of the Landtsgraues body at the meeting of which, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that excuſeth teares in euills remedileſſe, diſpenſed not with her without aboundance. Many great Lords of <hi>Germany &amp; Sicely,</hi> who had perfourmed this laſt office to this great Prince, ſeeing his widowe was reduced to ſtraights vnworthy the Houſe from whence shee ſprang, gaue <hi>Henry</hi> to vnderſtand they would not depart the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, vntill she were reſtored to an eſtate ſuteable to her worth, &amp; that they reſolued to enforce him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. Hee allowed her one of the good lieſt houſes of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try for her habitation, whereof she made vſe not to liue, but that shee might learne to dye therein. Piety
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:1248:42"/>
which with her was of more valew then life, chaunged this Caſtle into a monaſtery, where she liued with vnſpeakable auſterity.</p>
            <p>Good bloud makes not more haſt to the wounded part, then the king of <hi>Hungary</hi> aduertiſed of the Landtsgraues death, did to the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of his daughter to comfort her. He dearely loued her, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hee had other children, hee kept moſt loue in ſtore for her, as the Eagle euer affecteth one of her young more then the reſt. But being informed she deſpiſed the world, he diſpatched a principall lord of his Court to intreat her (and, if commaunds were not powerfull enough, to adde thereunto the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of a king to cauſe her,) to retourne into <hi>Hungary,</hi> as alſo in the meane tyme to aſſure her, that as the glory and meritt of the ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1248:42"/>
which the Prince her Husband had done to Chriſtendome remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for a Comfort, &amp; increaſe of ſtate &amp; patrimony to his children, ſo it inclyned his diſpoſition to let her ſee this accident should not in any ſort impayre her condition.</p>
            <p>But he found her nothing flexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his perſwaſions, nor well pleaſed with his propoſitions. Her eyes were too cleare, not to knowe that the gould of worldly promiſes is ſophiſticate, and that as the Sunne canot be better ſeene, then in cleare &amp; pure water, ſoe true content of minde, may not rightly be eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but in Soules purged &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifyed from the cares and embroyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the world.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Behold her Fathers letter.</head>
                  <p>Daughter, Fortune aſſayleth, not for ſlight cauſes the courages of thoſe who are of your quality: she hath
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:1248:43"/>
inuaded you on that ſide where she thought to ouercome your conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and triumph ouer your vertue. It is the death of the Landtsgraue which extreamely grieues me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you haue loſt a good Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and the Chriſtian world a great Captayne. My affliction is ſo much the more harsh and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable to me, in that I heard of his death before his malady, and that one and the ſame inſtant ſawe me to applaude the ſucceſſe of his voyage, the miracles of his life, and to bewayle the accident of his death. I should wrong your iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to comfort you, in matters, which you vnderſtand to be reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dileſſe. I had rather aſſure you, that he who called your Husband to heauen, reſerueth a Father for you on earth, more deſirous then euer, to make you ſo happy by a ſecond
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:1248:43"/>
mariage as you had occaſion to be pleaſed with your firſt. Abillity in me shall not be more difficult, then will. But I shall euer leaue your diſpoſition at liberty, moſt confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent you will not inclyne it to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions contrary to the age whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein you are, nor to the counſells of thoſe who loued you before you were capable of loue. Come hether then to reape the fruits, &amp; afford this contentment to the deſires, and prayers of your father.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Andrew.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>SHe was not much troubled what aunſwere she should make to this letter; with the ſame hand wherewith she receiued it, she wrote theſe lynes, ſaying as <hi>Olympius,</hi> that if God had been pleaſed she should haue continued in the company of a man, he neuer had bereaued her of a husband.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:1248:44"/>
                  <p>S.<hi rend="sup">r</hi> (ſayd she) I cannot thinke God hath called one moity of my ſelfe to heauen, to ſuffer the other any long tyme to languish heere, and though for his iuſtice ſake, &amp; the punishment of my ſinnes, it should pleaſe him to prolong my dayes, it will not be to reduce me backe againe into the ſeruitude from which I am freed. As to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfye you, I loued no man but my Lord the Landtsgraue, ſo for his loue none liuing shall be affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by me, to poſſeſſe either my heart, or body. I gaue vnto the world the flowers &amp; fruits of mine age, you ought not to thinke it amiſſe, if I reſerue for heauen the laſt honour of the tree, and that poore verdure which in the ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide thereof already beginneth to waxe pale, &amp; withered; an euident ſigne that the immutable renoua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:1248:44"/>
which I hartily wish, is not farre of. If you hinder the vowes I haue made of perpetuall continency, you shall be the ſole authour of my death, as you were one of the cauſes of my life. Your Court whereu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to you inuite me shall be to me a death, life a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the world a hell; you shall chaunge the name of a Father into that, which can noe way belong to you, but by forcing a will which God him ſelfe permitts to be free, in her who remayning his faithfull ſeruant, deſires alſo to reſt your moſt humble Daughter.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Elizabeth.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The king of <hi>Hungary</hi> hearing this reſolution, did all he could to diuert her from it. Many Princes vpon the bruit of ſoe aboundant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, wherewith she replenished all <hi>Europe</hi> ſought her in a ſecond wedlocke. Shee continually expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:1248:45"/>
she neither could, nor would marry. That if her excuſes were not taken for denyalls, and her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions for reaſons, she would ſlitt her noſe, thruſt out her eyes, ſo disfigure her ſelfe, that not any should deſire her. From that tyme forward she became the fable, and floute of the world, the ſcorne of great ones, the shame and rebuke of her neareſt Allyes, her zeale was accounted folly, her deuotion hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy, her ſimplicity ſottishneſſe her retiredneſſe melancholy. Some ſayd vnto her she did well to liue more vertuouſlie &amp; piouſly then the reſt of her ſexe, but to liue leſſe noblie was baſeneſſe, and in this extraordinarie manner meere giddineſſe.</p>
            <p>Another life, another manner of liuing. We muſt in matter of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as in nauigation beyond the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:1248:45"/>
Pole arctique, haue another heauen, other ſtarres, another Pole. When one is arriued to this point of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking the world, another ſcience muſt be learned, another ſpiritt, another intention, when we looſe the North ſtarre of will, wee muſt take vnto vs, that, of obedience. The life of thoſe great ſoules, which liue in Heauen although they breath on earth, hath a courſe much contrary to that of the world as the ſtarres.</p>
            <p>All the actions of this Princeſſe directed to the honour of God, ſtood out the shott of the arrowes of enuy and Calumny. She no whitt regarded, what the people (bad cenſurers of good workes) ſayed of her. She reioyced when thoſe bladders of ſlaunder emptyed them ſelues on her of the poyſon, wherewith they were filled.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:1248:46"/>Beſides her heart was ſoe large and ample, that theſe petty iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes were quite loſt vpon her, her Soule onely liuing on wormewood, had noe gall in it.</p>
            <p>The innocency, and ſimplicity of her life had the ſame vertues againſt calumnyes, which the little ſtones of Nilus, that keepe dogges from barking. The wicked in the end were conſtrayned to chaunge their ſcorne into admiration of a life, more like to that of Angells then of mortalls.</p>
            <p>She rayſed her arme to the higheſt triumph whereunto vertue might reach, not onely tollerating iniuryes, but doing good to any that wronged her. Some maleuolent tongues thinking to fixe the ſting of their ſlaunders vpon her memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the more to afflict her, ſpake ill of her, and touched her to the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:1248:46"/>
quicke, although the innocency of her life, and the purity of her actions made her inſenſible of ſuch woundes: but naturallie, falshoods vexe and penetrate the Soule more then truthes. All her reuenge was to pray to God for the calumnious, and in this her oraiſon, shee heard a voyce from heauen, aſſuring her that of ſoe many prayers as were made by her, that, which she offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the behalfe of her enemyes had been the moſt acceptable.</p>
            <p>Euery one ſawe the euill she ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, and not any the good she did, her night watchings and auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rityes. Such holy actions are lighted torches, ſuddenlie put out with the firſt blaſt of vanity, and preſumption, if humility couer them not.</p>
            <p>In this long and tedious way she neuer looked backward, nor ſtayed at the golden apples, to ſlacken her
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:1248:47"/>
ſpeed. The more she drewe nigh ro her end, the more she deſired to attayne it. The nearer she ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached to the center, the more ſtable she became. She was a wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe at twenty yeares of age, she vowed her ſelfe to the third order of <hi>Saint Frauncis</hi> at twenty one, wherin she liued and died happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. She went out of the world, as out of a Babilon, finding nothing therein to ſatisfye her ſoule, nor to eaſe the langours, or shorten the length of the miſerable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life, where the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous waxe olde, rather with anxiety, then yeares.</p>
            <p>A reſolution truly worthy of a heart ſo reſolute. It onely apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth to generous hearts to reſolue vpon ſo violent chaunges, and to make ſuch leapes from earth to heauen.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:1248:47"/>She liued and died ſo bleſſedly, &amp; the ſanctity of her life was teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed by ſo many miracles, that Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the nynth in full Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell declared her a Saint, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned the 27. of Nouember for her feſtiuall. Her body fower yeares after her death wholly entire, and odoriferous, was taken out of the earth, and ſett vpon the Aultar of a Church dedicated to her name by the Archbishops of <hi>Colen, Mentz,</hi> and <hi>Breme.</hi> The Emperour was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the ceremony, and to this Princeſſe (who liuing deſpiſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall crownes, for that of thornes) hee preſented a triple crowne of gould, as a witneſſe of the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions which had crowned the three conditions of her life. Shee had three children, <hi>Herman</hi> who ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded his Father, and dyed at the age of Eighteene yeares, <hi>Sophia</hi> that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:1248:48"/>
was marryed to the Duke of Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, &amp; another <hi>Sophia,</hi> who follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the piety of her mother be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came religious at <hi>Kitzing in Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold how impoſſible it is to ſpeake ill of thoſe who haue liued well.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1248:48"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
